<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[keighty]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-04T14:58:03-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[katie leonard]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[TDD and the Senior Software Engineer]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2015/the-senior-software-engineer/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-04T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2015/the-senior-software-engineer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Many developers embrace test-driven development (TDD) as an ideal but rarely put it into practice. I often find myself writing code that works and then writing tests that exercise it to ensure that its behaviour doesn&rsquo;t break when changes are made. Writing tests first is a great way to organize your approach to solving a problem, and in <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Senior-Software-Engineer-Practices-Effective/dp/0990702804/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1420403139&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=on+being+a+senior+engineer"><strong>The Senior Software Engineer</strong></a>, David Copeland describes how TDD will help you grow your career as well.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>A senior software engineer is efficient, and delivers a quality product in a timely fashion. <span class='pullquote-left' data-pullquote='Effective problem solvers first spend time understanding the problem space and then design a plan'>Effective problem solvers first spend time understanding the problem space and then design a plan: documenting feature behaviour in a test suite allows you to plan your implementation. Code maintenance and modification are also more efficient when you have a good test suite. If the code has been built using TDD, its behaviour is already well tested. When someone needs to build on top of your feature, the tests will protect it and eliminate the worry of causing regressions (win-win).
</span></p>

<p>Explicitly describing your plan in a test suite has another benefit that I had not considered before, and that is making you resilient to interruption. If your plan is not layed out on paper, you are maintaining it all in your head, and you have to hold on to a lot of context in your working memory. <span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='TDD can help you structure your coding task so that it has natural breaking points. If you are interrupted while trying to fix a failing test, you know exactly where you can pick the task up again.'>Every time you are interrupted, you have to dump things out of your working memory, and reloading the problem space takes time and energy. You won&rsquo;t suffer interruptions well if reloading the context takes 15 minutes each time. You will become unresponsive as you block out the outside world, trying to maintain your context.</p>

<p>TDD can help you structure your coding task so that it has natural breaking points. If you are interrupted while trying to fix a failing test, you know exactly where you can pick the task up again. If you are interrupted after getting a test to pass you can easily read through your test suite to regain your context and pick up the next task.
</span></p>

<p>Time and context management are essential skills for becoming a senior software engineer, and I am going to try using test driven development to become more interruptable and more productive.</p>

<!-- RESOURCES
* http://act-r.psy.cmu.edu/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/448preparing.to.resume.pdf
* http://interruptions.net/literature/Fogarty-CHI05-p331-fogarty.pdf
* http://contenthere.net/2012/10/what-it-takes-to-be-a-senior-engineer.html
* http://www.amazon.com/Senior-Software-Engineer-Practices-Effective/dp/0990702804/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&qid=1420403139&sr=8-1&keywords=on+being+a+senior+engineer
* [The Senior Software Engineer](http://www.amazon.com/Senior-Software-Engineer-Practices-Effective/dp/0990702804/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&qid=1420403139&sr=8-1&keywords=on+being+a+senior+engineer) by David Bryant Copeland

OUTLINE
Test-driven development can help you grow your career.
1. test-driven development is an ideal that many strive for and few embrace.
2. many developers embrace the ideas of test-driven development, but few practice it rigorously.
3. writing tests is important to delivering quality, robust code, and is essential for writing code that you ever hope to change.
4. did you know that test-driven development can help you grow your career as well?
-->

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Octopress Reloaded]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2015/octopress-reloaded/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-03T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2015/octopress-reloaded</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently upgraded my home hardware from an <a href="http://www.amazon.com/ASUS-1000HE-10-1-Inch-Black-Netbook/dp/B001QTXL82">Asus 10.1&#8221; netbook</a> to a <a href="https://www.apple.com/macbook-pro/">15&#8221; MacBook Pro</a>, and once I adjusted to being able to open more than one window at a time, I got down to the business of loading my files and projects on the new machine. Thanks to <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/">Dropbox</a> and <a href="https://github.com/">Github</a>, most of that work happens either behind the scenes or as needed. Recreating the right environment for each project is still ongoing, and the first challenge I encountered was reloading my blog &mdash; started about two years ago using <a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a>.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Octopress is an awesome framework built on <a href="http://jekyllrb.com/">jekyll</a>. The learning curve for getting started with jekyll was a little steep (liquid layouts, yaml, not to mention design and UX were all new to me then) , and Octopress delivers on its promise to make it easy: just clone, bundle, and blog. Part of what makes Octopress so awesome is the deploy strategy: static pages are generated from yaml and markdown sources (saved in the source branch), and the pages are checked in to your github or heroku repository (as the master branch).</p>

<p>When you clone the repo, you get both branches, but you have to do a little setup to ensure that master is pulling from and pushing to the right place. Borrowing some code from the <a href="https://github.com/imathis/octopress/blob/master/Rakefile#L351-L358">setup rake task</a>:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>git clone git@github.com:username/username.github.com.git my_blog
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span><span class="nb">cd </span>my_blog
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>git checkout <span class="nb">source</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>mkdir _deploy
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span><span class="nb">cd </span>_deploy
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>git init
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>git remote add origin git@github.com:username/username.github.com.git
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>git pull origin master
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span><span class="nb">cd</span> ..
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>bundle install
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>bundle <span class="nb">exec </span>rake preview
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Now I have no excuses to not blog more often&hellip; well, fewer excuses (thanks to <a href="http://code.dblock.org/octopress-setting-up-a-blog-and-contributing-to-an-existing-one">Daniel Doubrovkine</a> for pointing me in the right direction).</p>

<p>I briefly considered switching to a hosted blogging platform (tumblr or wordpress), so I conducted an informal survey (sample size taken from <a href="https://www.digitalocean.com/company/blog/20-developers-to-follow-in-2014/">Digital Ocean&rsquo;s 20 developers to follow</a>) to see what choices leading developers were making, and it looks like a jekyll based blog is still the most popular. What is yours?</p>



<table class="tg">
  <tr>
    <th class="tg-031e">platform</th>
    <th class="tg-031e">users</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td class="tg-s6z2">jekyll</td>
    <td class="tg-031e">6</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td class="tg-031e">octopress</td>
    <td class="tg-031e">3</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td class="tg-031e">none</td>
    <td class="tg-031e">3</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td class="tg-031e">tumblr</td>
    <td class="tg-031e">1</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td class="tg-031e">hand-rolled</td>
    <td class="tg-031e">6</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td class="tg-031e">wordpress</td>
    <td class="tg-031e">1</td>
  </tr>
</table>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Happiness Hypothesis]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2015/the-happiness-hypothesis/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2015/the-happiness-hypothesis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>&ldquo;Nothing is miserable unless you think it so; and on the other hand, nothing brings happiness unless you are content with it.&rdquo; &mdash;Buddha</p></blockquote>

<p>In <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Happiness-Hypothesis-Finding-Modern-Ancient/dp/0465028020/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1420146441&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+happiness+hypothesis">The Happiness Hypothesis</a>: Finding Modern Truth in Ancient Wisdom, Jonathan Haidt provides an extensive overview of the state of positive psychology today.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>He uses the analogy of a rider on an elephant to describe how the mind is divided into two parts: the conscious, reasoning part (the rider), and the unconscious mind that is actually driving our behaviour (the elephant). Stepping in to the New Year, the twitter-verse is alive with resolutions to eat less, exercise more, and spend less money &mdash; all laudable goals for the rider, but unless you can re-train the elephant to want those same things, you will find yourself in line for a 16oz hot chocolate with whipped cream by the end of the week.</p>

<h3>On the happiness equation: H = S + C + V</h3>

<blockquote><p>The level of happiness that you actually experience (H) is determined by your biological set point (S) plus the conditions of your life &copy; plus the voluntary activities (V) you do.</p></blockquote>

<p>This has certainly been true in my life. I tend towards a positive outlook (as Haidt describes it, a winner of the &lsquo;cortical lottery&rsquo;), but that doesn&rsquo;t mean I don&rsquo;t experience ups and downs brought on by circumstances and choices. Changing your level of happiness can come from changing your circumstances, or by participating in rewarding acitivites. (Out of ideas? Try <a href="http://www.bodyvox.com/classes/beginning-ballet-and-wine-tasting-0">beginning ballet and wine tasting</a>!)</p>

<h3>On training the elephant</h3>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;The goal of meditation is to change automatic thought processes, thereby taming the elephant. And the proof of taming is the breaking of attachments&hellip; For Buddha, attachments are like a game of roulette in which someone else spins the wheel and the game is rigged: The more you play, the more you lose. The only way to win is to step away from the table. And the only way to step away, to make yourself not react to the ups and downs of life, is to meditate and tame the mind. Although you give up the pleasures of winning, you also give up the larger pains of losing.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<p>I like the idea of training the elephant through meditation, but disagree with the pursuit of non-attachment. Living life without any attachments means missing out on joy as well as pain. If life is an amuzement park, is it better to spend your time on the teacups or the rollercoaster? Isn&rsquo;t it better to have loved and lost than never to have loved at all?</p>

<h3>On your inner lawyer</h3>

<blockquote><p>[People] are skilled at finding reasons to support their gut feelings. The rider acts like a lawyer whom the elephant has hired to represent it in the court of public opinion&hellip; Studies of everyday reasoning show that&hellip; when people are given difficult questions to think about&hellip; they generally lean one way or the other right away, and then put a call in to reasoning to see whether support for that position is forthcoming.</p></blockquote>

<p>I love the idea of our conscious mind acting as a lawyer defending our actions and decisions. We only look for supporting evidence, and any data that undermines our world-view must be discredited or its importance downplayed.</p>

<h3>On reciprocation and gossip</h3>

<blockquote><p>A species equipped with vengeance and gratitude responses can support larger and more cooperative social groups because the payoff to cheaters is reduced by the costs they bear in making enemies&hellip; Tit for tat appears to be built into human nature as a set of moral emotions that make us want to return favor for favor, insult for insult&hellip;</p></blockquote>

<p>Social groups cannot be formed without cooperation and a set of norms. Norms can be enforced through gossip:</p>

<blockquote><p>Many species reciprocate, but only humans gossip, and much of what we gossip about is the value of other people as partners for reciprocal relationships&hellip; Gossip paired with reciprocity allow karma to work here on eatch, not in the next life.</p></blockquote>

<h3>On writing your life story</h3>

<blockquote><p>The third level of personality is that of the &ldquo;life story.&rdquo; Human beings in every culture are fascinated by stories; we create them wherever we can.. It&rsquo;s no different with our own lives. We can&rsquo;t stop ourselves from creating what McAdams describes as an &ldquo;evolving story that integrates a reconstructed past, perceived present, and anticipated future into a coherent and vitalizing life myth.&rdquo; Although the lowest level of personality is mostly about the elephant, the life story is written primarily by the rider. You create your story in consciousness as you interpret your own behavior, and as you listen to other people&rsquo;s thoughts about you.</p></blockquote>

<p>Every time I relate a personal anecdote to a new listener I find that I am refining the narrative &mdash; using the same words and phrases, pausing at the same moments each time. My partner and I have developed a cadence when we tell people about our drive across Canada, or our trip to the Maritimes. We are building our life story through relatable moments.</p>

<h3>On growing through adversity</h3>

<blockquote><p>Be sure you have done your best to answer these two questions: Why did this happen? What good might I derive from it?</p></blockquote>

<p>Whatever doesn&rsquo;t kill you doesn&rsquo;t always make you stronger, but we can grow through adversity. Pain doesn&rsquo;t always equal gain, but a root cause analysis (why did this happen?), and reframing to find something positive in the experience (lessons learned), is a great approach.</p>

<h3>On the ideological differences in moral ethics:</h3>

<blockquote><p>The ethic of autonomy, the ethic of community, and the ethic of divinity.</p></blockquote>

<p>Policial and ideological differences arise from approaching life from different moral perspectives. In the ethic of autonomy, the goal is to protect individuals from harm and interference. In the ethic of community the goal is to protect the integrity of groups, families, companies, or nations, and its virtues are obedience, and loyalty. In the ethic of divinity, the goal is to protect the sacred from the profane. They value living in a pure and holy way, free from pollutants such as lust, greed, and hatred.</p>

<h3>Vital engagement (or flow)</h3>

<blockquote><p>Vital engagement does not reside in the person or in the environment; it exists in the relationship between the two.</p></blockquote>

<p>Memories that encorporate more than one sensation are the strongest. Similarly, finding meaning and flow in an activity requires more than just a connection through commitment. There must be connections through a community, a shared history, and a shared experience. I didn&rsquo;t come to love programming because it seemed like a rewarding career path. I built a script that was useful to a coworker, drew excitment from other programmers, and began peeling back the layers of abstraction, enjoying the &lsquo;A-ha!&rsquo; when understanding occurred.</p>

<h3>On happiness and the meaning of life</h3>

<blockquote><p>Happiness is not something that you can find, acquire, or achieve directly. You have to get the conidtions right and then wait.</p></blockquote>

<p>This is the first book I have read that really tried to approach the meaning of life, and my inner elephant has decided that Haidt is on the right track.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Method Lookup in Ruby]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/method-lookup-in-ruby/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-28T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/method-lookup-in-ruby</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have once more been working my way through Sandi Metz&#8217; <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Practical-Object-Oriented-Design-Ruby-Addison-Wesley/dp/0321721330">Practical Object-oriented Design in Ruby</a> (POODR) for a few weeks, and developed a mental block about method lookup.</p>

<p>In Chapter 6 (Acquiring behaviour through inheritance), she describes how to extract a superclass from a group of related classes that share some behaviour by pulling methods up the inheritance chain instead of driving specializations down. This approach ensures a clean abstraction, leaving no specialized behaviour in the superclass. Where I got stuck was in the call chain that enforces the common interface:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
<span class='line-number'>21</span>
<span class='line-number'>22</span>
<span class='line-number'>23</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'><span class="k">class</span> <span class="nc">Foo</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">initialize</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">baz</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">baz</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">raise</span> <span class="no">NotImplementedError</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">new</span> <span class="s2">&quot;You can&#39;t call #baz here!&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">class</span> <span class="nc">Bar</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span> <span class="no">Foo</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">initialize</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">super</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">baz</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nb">puts</span> <span class="s2">&quot;Hello, baz&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="n">x</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="no">Bar</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">new</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="s2">&quot;Hello, baz&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="c1">#&lt;Bar:0x007fc4f903ab90&gt;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>I could not understand why, the <code>NotImplementedError</code> wasn&rsquo;t raised when a new <code>Bar</code> was created. This is how I imagined the call stack should work:</p>

<ol>
<li><code>Bar.new</code> calls <code>Bar#initialize</code></li>
<li><code>Bar</code> calls <code>super</code> (<code>Foo#initialize</code>)</li>
<li><code>Foo</code> calls <code>baz</code> (<code>Foo#baz</code>)</li>
<li>raises <code>NotImplementedError</code></li>
</ol>


<p>This is how the call stack actually works</p>

<ol>
<li><code>x = Bar.new</code> calls <code>Bar#initialize</code></li>
<li><code>x</code> receives a call to <code>super</code> (<code>Foo#initalize</code>)</li>
<li><code>x</code> receives a call to <code>baz</code> (<code>Bar#baz</code>)</li>
<li>says &ldquo;Hello, baz&rdquo;</li>
</ol>


<p>The call never comes from the context of <code>Foo</code> &mdash; the receiver is always <code>x</code>, the instance of <code>Bar</code>. Classical inheritance dictates that an object can only look to itself or further up the inheritance chain for valid method definitions, not down. <code>x</code> is reaching up to call <code>super</code> but checks itself for an answer to the question <code>#baz</code>. <code>Foo#baz</code> would only ever be called if we made a new <code>Foo</code> directly:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'><span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="n">y</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="no">Foo</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">new</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="ss">NotImplementedError</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="no">You</span> <span class="n">can</span><span class="s1">&#39;t call #baz here!</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="s1">        from (irb):7:in `baz&#39;</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="n">from</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">irb</span><span class="p">):</span><span class="mi">3</span><span class="ss">:in</span> <span class="sb">`initialize&#39;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="sb">        from (irb):27:in `</span><span class="kp">new</span><span class="s1">&#39;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="s1">        from (irb):27</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="s1">        from /usr/local/var/rbenv/versions/2.1.5/bin/irb:11:in `&lt;main&gt;&#39;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>How ruby resolves a message (classical inheritance)</h3>

<p>The search for a method begins in the class of the receiving object &mdash; in the example above, Bar is always the receiving object. If the class does not implement the message, the search proceeds up the superclass chain. If none of the superclasses contain the method definition, ruby makes a second attempt to resolve the message by sending <code>method_missing(:method_name)</code> to the original object. The search restarts from the bottom, but this time for a <code>method_missing</code> handler rather than <code>:method_name</code>.</p>

<p>Occasionally refreshing the ruby basics is super-rewarding.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Helpers Calling Helpers]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/helpers-calling-helpers/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/helpers-calling-helpers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Whittling away at the Discover Meteor tutorial for creating a social news sharing site, I was implementing a Comments collection and related accoutrements (templates, helpers, forms, etc.) when I uncovered a need to call one helper method from another<!--more-->.</p>

<p>I was using this handy method to return the number of comments made on a particular post:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Helpful helpers </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='js'><span class='line'><span class="nx">Template</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">postPageItem</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">helpers</span><span class="p">({</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">commentsCount</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="nx">Comments</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">find</span><span class="p">({</span><span class="nx">postId</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="k">this</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">_id</span><span class="p">}).</span><span class="nx">count</span><span class="p">();</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">});</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>




<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Template helper magic sauce </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='js'><span class='line'><span class="nx">submitted</span> <span class="nx">by</span> <span class="p">{{</span><span class="nx">postAuthor</span><span class="p">}},</span> <span class="kd">with</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nx">a</span> <span class="nx">href</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">&quot;{{pathFor &#39;postPage&#39;}}&quot;</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="p">{{</span><span class="nx">commentsCount</span><span class="p">}}</span> <span class="nx">comments</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="err">/a&gt;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Which returned a very ordinary:</p>

<blockquote><p>submitted by meImAnAwesomeUser, with 1 comments</p></blockquote>

<p>1 <strong>comments</strong>?! That makes no sense.. I didn&rsquo;t minor in English so I could let that travesty fly. I made a new helper method:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>This WORKS! </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='js'><span class='line'><span class="nx">Template</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">postPageItem</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">helpers</span><span class="p">({</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">commentsCount</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="nx">Comments</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">find</span><span class="p">({</span><span class="nx">postId</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="k">this</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">_id</span><span class="p">}).</span><span class="nx">count</span><span class="p">();</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">},</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">commentsNote</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="nx">Comments</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">find</span><span class="p">({</span><span class="nx">postId</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="k">this</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">_id</span><span class="p">}).</span><span class="nx">count</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="o">===</span> <span class="mi">1</span> <span class="o">?</span> <span class="s2">&quot;comment&quot;</span> <span class="o">:</span> <span class="s2">&quot;comments&quot;</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">});</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>UGH! What is that on line 6? Possibly the ugliest ternary statement I have written today (probably). Is that code duplication I smell? Won&rsquo;t reusing <code>commentsCount</code> remove the redundancy?</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Starting to DRY the meteor </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='js'><span class='line'><span class="nx">Template</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">postPageItem</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">helpers</span><span class="p">({</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">commentsCount</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="nx">Comments</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">find</span><span class="p">({</span><span class="nx">postId</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="k">this</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">_id</span><span class="p">}).</span><span class="nx">count</span><span class="p">();</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">},</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">commentsNote</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="nx">commentsCount</span> <span class="o">===</span> <span class="mi">1</span> <span class="o">?</span> <span class="s2">&quot;comment&quot;</span> <span class="o">:</span> <span class="s2">&quot;comments&quot;</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">});</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Only.. that doesn&rsquo;t work:</p>

<pre><code>Exception from Deps recompute function: ReferenceError: commentsCount is not defined
at Object.Template.postPageItem.helpers.commentsNote (http://localhost:3000/client/views/posts/post_page_item.js?160ec9a926881c795377a47c15affc4f553c4d88:9:12)
</code></pre>

<p>But it is RIGHT ABOVE! I can see it! It is in the same file! I tried all permutations of <code>commentsCount()</code>, <code>this.commentsCount</code>, <code>self.commentsCount</code>, <code>this.self.commentsCount()</code>, and they all threw either similar errors or <code>undefined</code>. Calling the prototype method directly turns out to work just fine:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>THIS is not THAT and also doesn&#8217;t work </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='js'><span class='line'><span class="nx">Template</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">postPageItem</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">helpers</span><span class="p">({</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">commentsCount</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="nx">Comments</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">find</span><span class="p">({</span><span class="nx">postId</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="k">this</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">_id</span><span class="p">}).</span><span class="nx">count</span><span class="p">();</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">},</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">commentsNote</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">count</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">Template</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">postPageItem</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">commentsCount</span><span class="p">()</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="nx">count</span> <span class="o">===</span> <span class="mi">1</span> <span class="o">?</span> <span class="s2">&quot;comment&quot;</span> <span class="o">:</span> <span class="s2">&quot;comments&quot;</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">});</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Except that when <code>commentsCount</code> is called on line 6, <code>this</code> is no longer the lovely Post item provided by the template. No, <code>this</code> becomes the context of the <code>commentsNote</code> function, and therefore calling <code>this._id</code> will return <code>undefined</code>. The closure issue can be worked around with a little argument passing:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Is DRY so much better? </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='js'><span class='line'><span class="nx">Template</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">postPageItem</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">helpers</span><span class="p">({</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">commentsCount</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">id</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">count_id</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="k">typeof</span> <span class="nx">id</span> <span class="o">!==</span> <span class="s1">&#39;undefined&#39;</span> <span class="o">?</span> <span class="nx">id</span> <span class="o">:</span> <span class="k">this</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">_id</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="nx">Comments</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">find</span><span class="p">({</span><span class="nx">postId</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="nx">count_id</span><span class="p">}).</span><span class="nx">count</span><span class="p">();</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">},</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">commentsNote</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">count</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">Template</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">postPageItem</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">commentsCount</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="k">this</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">_id</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="nx">count</span> <span class="o">===</span> <span class="mi">1</span> <span class="o">?</span> <span class="s2">&quot;comment&quot;</span> <span class="o">:</span> <span class="s2">&quot;comments&quot;</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">});</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Wow. Passing in the id works, but now I have to check the context to determine the appropriate id. That is the most unreadable-but-reused code I have written today (probably), and I learned some valuable lessons on this frantic search for DRY:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>self</code>, whether called from a helper or the console, will always be <code>window</code></li>
<li><code>this</code> called from a Template helper refers to the item of the collection that is passed in to the template</li>
<li>because helper methods are closures, <code>this</code> in the calling method is different from <code>this</code> in the called method</li>
<li>don&rsquo;t dry out your code to the point of unreadability</li>
</ul>


<p>In the end, cleaning up the ugly ternary makes the code reuse more reasonable.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>This is just fine </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='js'><span class='line'><span class="nx">Template</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">postPageItem</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">helpers</span><span class="p">({</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">commentsCount</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="nx">Comments</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">find</span><span class="p">({</span><span class="nx">postId</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="k">this</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">_id</span><span class="p">}).</span><span class="nx">count</span><span class="p">();</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">},</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">commentsNote</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">count</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">Comments</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">find</span><span class="p">({</span><span class="nx">postId</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="k">this</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">_id</span><span class="p">}).</span><span class="nx">count</span><span class="p">();</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="nx">count</span> <span class="o">===</span> <span class="mi">1</span> <span class="o">?</span> <span class="s2">&quot;comment&quot;</span> <span class="o">:</span> <span class="s2">&quot;comments&quot;</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">});</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Awesome.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Flash Your Local Collection]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/flash-your-local-collection/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-26T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/flash-your-local-collection</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Rails allows you to pass messages to the user between actions (&ldquo;This <a href="http://api.rubyonrails.org/classes/ActionDispatch/Flash.html">ActionDispatch::Flash</a> will self-destruct&rdquo;), and because Rails, all the message generation happens server side:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>flashy_controller.rb </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">show</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">flash</span><span class="o">[</span><span class="ss">:notice</span><span class="o">]</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="s2">&quot;You dropped your packet.&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">end</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Meteor is mostly a client-side application framework, and you can implement a similar message system, which will never touch the server, by defining a collection that is local to the browser.<!--more--></p>

<h3>1. Create a local collection</h3>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>/client/errors.js </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='js'><span class='line'><span class="nx">Errors</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="k">new</span> <span class="nx">Meteor</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">Collection</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kc">null</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Passing <code>null</code> into the Collection declaration tells Meteor that the collection should not be extended to the server &mdash; it creates an &ldquo;unmanaged (unsynchronized) local collection&rdquo; (<a href="http://docs.meteor.com/#meteor_collection">docs</a>)</p>

<h3>2. Throw an error whenever you need to</h3>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>/missionCritical.js </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='html'><span class='line'>if(error){
</span><span class='line'>  Errors.insert({message: error.reason});
</span><span class='line'>}
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>3. Create a template for displaying the error</h3>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>/client/errors.html </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='js'><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nx">template</span> <span class="nx">name</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">&quot;errors&quot;</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nx">div</span> <span class="kr">class</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">&quot;errors&quot;</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">{{</span><span class="err">#</span><span class="nx">each</span> <span class="nx">errors</span><span class="p">}}</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="p">{{</span><span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="nx">error</span><span class="p">}}</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">{{</span><span class="err">/each}}</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="err">/div&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="err">/template&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nx">template</span> <span class="nx">name</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">&quot;error&quot;</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nx">div</span> <span class="kr">class</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">&quot;alert alert-error&quot;</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nx">button</span> <span class="nx">type</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">&quot;button&quot;</span> <span class="kr">class</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">&quot;close&quot;</span> <span class="nx">data</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="nx">dismiss</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">&quot;alert&quot;</span><span class="o">&gt;&amp;</span><span class="nx">times</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="err">/button&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">{{</span><span class="nx">message</span><span class="p">}}</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="err">/div&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="err">/template&gt;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>4. Create a helper method for serving the errors to the template</h3>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>/client/errors.js continued again </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='js'><span class='line'><span class="p">...</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nx">Template</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">errors</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">helpers</span><span class="p">({</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">errors</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="nx">Errors</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">find</span><span class="p">();</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Every template that contains the handlebars <code>{{&gt; errors}}</code> will now display whatever errors have been saved to the session collection.</p>

<p>Awesome.</p>

<h3>Resources</h3>

<p><a href="https://www.discovermeteor.com/">discovermeteor.com</a>
<a href="http://docs.meteor.com">Meteor docs</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mongo Trouble? Reset!]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/mongo-trouble-reset/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/mongo-trouble-reset</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Back in March I wrote about letting my computer&rsquo;s battery die in the middle of a meteor project, with the consequence being that I could not connect to the underlying mongo database:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>What&#8217;s wrong, meteor? </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>meteor
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">[[[[[</span> ~/project/in/progress <span class="o">]]]]]</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">=</span>&gt; Started proxy.
</span><span class='line'>Unexpected mongo <span class="nb">exit </span>code 100. Restarting.
</span><span class='line'>Unexpected mongo <span class="nb">exit </span>code 100. Restarting.
</span><span class='line'>Unexpected mongo <span class="nb">exit </span>code 100. Restarting.
</span><span class='line'>Can<span class="err">&#39;</span>t start Mongo server.
</span><span class='line'>MongoDB had an unspecified uncaught exception.
</span><span class='line'>This can be caused by MongoDB being unable to write to a <span class="nb">local </span>database.
</span><span class='line'>Check that you have permissions to write to .meteor/local. MongoDB does
</span><span class='line'>not support filesystems like NFS that <span class="k">do </span>not allow file locking.
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>After much spelunking in stackoverflow and documentation, I discovered the magic of this command:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Magic mongo reset spell %</span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>sudo -u mongodb mongdo --repair --dbpath /var/lib/mongodb
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>sudo service mongodb start
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Repairing and restarting the mongo service seemed to do the trick, and I continued on my merry meteor way. Well, I did it again &mdash; I let my battery die in the middle of a meteor project, and with feelings of smug satisfaction, I plumbed my blog archive for the answer. Only this time the magic antidote didn&rsquo;t work<!--more-->:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>This log has been redacted to protect the ignorant </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
<span class='line-number'>21</span>
<span class='line-number'>22</span>
<span class='line-number'>23</span>
<span class='line-number'>24</span>
<span class='line-number'>25</span>
<span class='line-number'>26</span>
<span class='line-number'>27</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>$ sudo -u mongodb mongod --repair --dbpath /var/lib/mongodb/
</span><span class='line'>[sudo] password for keighty:
</span><span class='line'>Sat May  3 09:52:04.793 [initandlisten] finished checking dbs
</span><span class='line'>Sat May  3 09:52:04.793 dbexit:
</span><span class='line'>Sat May  3 09:52:04.793 [initandlisten] shutdown: going to close listening sockets...
</span><span class='line'>Sat May  3 09:52:04.793 [initandlisten] shutdown: going to flush diaglog...
</span><span class='line'>Sat May  3 09:52:04.793 [initandlisten] shutdown: going to close sockets...
</span><span class='line'>Sat May  3 09:52:04.793 [initandlisten] shutdown: waiting for fs preallocator...
</span><span class='line'>Sat May  3 09:52:04.793 [initandlisten] shutdown: closing all files...
</span><span class='line'>Sat May  3 09:52:04.793 [initandlisten] closeAllFiles() finished
</span><span class='line'>Sat May  3 09:52:04.793 [initandlisten] shutdown: removing fs lock...
</span><span class='line'>Sat May  3 09:52:04.794 dbexit: really exiting now
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>$ sudo service mongodb start
</span><span class='line'>mongodb start/running, process 2415
</span><span class='line'>$ meteor
</span><span class='line'>[[[[[ ~/project/in/progress ]]]]]
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>=> Started proxy.
</span><span class='line'>Unexpected mongo exit code 100. Restarting.
</span><span class='line'>Unexpected mongo exit code 100. Restarting.
</span><span class='line'>Unexpected mongo exit code 100. Restarting.
</span><span class='line'>Can't start Mongo server.
</span><span class='line'>MongoDB had an unspecified uncaught exception.
</span><span class='line'>This can be caused by MongoDB being unable to write to a local database.
</span><span class='line'>Check that you have permissions to write to .meteor/local. MongoDB does
</span><span class='line'>not support filesystems like NFS that do not allow file locking.</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>C&#8217;mon &mdash; It worked the last time! I tried it again with the same result. I tried <code>chown</code>-ing the local db. I tried <code>chown</code>-ing the database in <code>/var/lib/mongodb</code>. After each attempted solution the mongobd service would start, but meteor hiccuped on writing to the database. So I tried something radical. Something that wasn&rsquo;t in any of the manuals, or any of the <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/5798549/why-cant-i-start-the-mongodb">responses to similar questions</a> on stackoverflow:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Really? That was all? </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>meteor reset
</span><span class='line'>Project reset.
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>meteor
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">[[[[[</span> ~/project/in/progress <span class="o">]]]]]</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">=</span>&gt; Started proxy.
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">=</span>&gt; Started MongoDB.
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">=</span>&gt; Started your app.
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">=</span>&gt; App running at: http://localhost:3000/
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Turns out that if you hard shut-down your computer while your meteor project&rsquo;s mongo instance is running, it remains in a locked mode. Since it was only a development database I took a chance that dropping it would cure my ills. Voila! Meteor and mongodb are friends again.</p>

<p>Awesome.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meteor, Fetch!]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/meteor-fetch/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-31T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/meteor-fetch</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>From <a href="http://book.discovermeteor.com/">Discover Meteor</a>: find() returns a cursor, which is a reactive data source.</p>

<p>Data from reactive sources will be updated automatically to track changes in the data used to generate it. <!--more-->Cursors are derived from specific sources:</p>

<ul>
<li>Session variables</li>
<li>Database queries on Collections</li>
<li>Meteor.status</li>
<li>The ready() method on a subscription handle</li>
<li>Meteor.user</li>
<li>Meteor.userId</li>
<li>Meteor.loggingIn</li>
</ul>


<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>For example, find() using a database query </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='js'><span class='line'><span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="nx">gt</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="nx">Posts</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">find</span><span class="p">()</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nx">LocalCollection</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">Cursor</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="nx">collection</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="nx">LocalCollection</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">sorter</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="kc">null</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">_selectorId</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="kc">undefined</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">matcher</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="nx">Minimongo</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">Matcher</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">skip</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="kc">undefined</span><span class="err"></span><span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nx">_selectorId</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="kc">undefined</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nx">_transform</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="kc">null</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nx">collection</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="nx">LocalCollection</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nx">cursor_pos</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="mi">0</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nx">db_objects</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="kc">null</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nx">fields</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="kc">undefined</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nx">limit</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="kc">undefined</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nx">matcher</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="nx">Minimongo</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">Matcher</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nx">reactive</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="kc">true</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nx">skip</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="kc">undefined</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nx">sorter</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="kc">null</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nx">__proto__</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="nb">Object</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Cursors are not query snapshots. They are query snapshot containers &mdash; the contents of which are updated by changes to the underlying data. To interact with the data contained in a cursor, we can use fetch() to transform the cursor into an array.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>A cursor becomes an array with find().fetch() </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='js'><span class='line'><span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="nx">gt</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="nx">Posts</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">find</span><span class="p">().</span><span class="nx">fetch</span><span class="p">()</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">[</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nb">Object</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">_id</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="s2">&quot;z4z36DFCaGr8Ptuqd&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">title</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="s2">&quot;The Way We Live Now&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">author</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="s2">&quot;Anthony Trollope&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">__proto__</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="nb">Object</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">...</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">]</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Meteor can iterate over a cursor without first converting it to an array, but in order to interact with the data directly, you must first use fetch(), map(), or forEach(). For more cursor fun, checkout the <a href="http://docs.meteor.com/#reactivity">Meteor docs</a>.</p>

<p>Awesome.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Situations Matter]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/situations-matter/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-28T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/situations-matter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Situations-Matter-Understanding-Context-Transforms-ebook/dp/B005ERIS5S/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1396016834&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=situations+matter">Situations Matter</a> by Sam Sommers is an eye-opening study of the influence of context on human interactions. Social psychologists call it &ldquo;fundamental attribution error&rdquo;, which is a tendency to interpret someone else&rsquo;s behavior as stemming from their core characteristics, rather than to external circumstances. A simplistic example of attribution error is assuming that the person driving the speeding car is a reckless speed-freak rather than someone rushing a woman in labor to the hospital. Sommers has studied the power of situations over human interactions and how the attribution error interferes with our ability to empathize with the unfamiliar. I have read similar studies of how bias infiltrates our relationships, but what surprised me the most is how it also influences our perception of the self. <!--more--></p>

<h3>You&rsquo;re not the person you thought you were</h3>

<p>A provocative but aptly named chapter, Sommers overturns the concept of an &ldquo;authentic self&rdquo; with a simple fill-in-the-blanks exercise:</p>

<ol>
<li>I am _________________</li>
<li>I am _________________</li>
<li>I am _________________</li>
<li>I am _________________</li>
<li>I am _________________</li>
</ol>


<p>His study subjects were required to fill in 20 of these blanks, but 5 is enough to illustrate his point to the reader. The open-endedness of this exercise allows for a fantastic range of responses: &ldquo;I am 36 years old, I am hungry, I am tall, I am a lifelong learner&rdquo;. Taking the 20 questions test in different contexts will yield different definitions of yourself. Sommers has discovered that &ldquo;we tend to think of ourselves in terms of that which makes us distinctive&rdquo;, so your answers will have more to do with the people around you than with a fixed set of characteristics. A woman is more likely to include gender on her list if she is in a room full of men than if she is in a room full of women. So it seems that &ldquo;identity is malleable and personal preferences are constructed on the spot.&rdquo; Introspection will gain us little but a hazy snap-shot of our identity at any given moment.</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;It&rsquo;s refreshing to realize that you&rsquo;re not a finished product &mdash; that who you are in the here and now may not be the same person you&rsquo;ll be in the then and there. In fact, it&rsquo;s the opposite view of the self as a fixed entity that causes problems. When you assume that there&rsquo;s a true core self waiting to be discovered, that&rsquo;s when your potential seems limited and the world around you is full of threats to be rationalized away.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<p>One quality that is typically presumed to be fixed is intelligence. Challenging this truism, another study was conducted where students were grouped according to their belief that either intelligence is a stable attribute, or that their intellect can be changed. The researchers asked the students to predict the likelihood that they will attend a remedial language course, and then tracked their performance. It was found that among the students who fared poorly in the language course, those who viewed intelligence as a permanent, unchangeable trait were less likely to enroll in the remedial course &mdash; that is, to take steps in order to improve their performance. For students who believe that intelligence is fixed, a poor exam grade is a mark of their limitations rather than an opportunity for improvement. Students who believe that intelligence is malleable are more likely to show the stick-to-itiveness necessary for self-improvement.</p>

<p>Viewing the self less like a rigid Rubik&rsquo;s Cube to be solved, and more like Silly Putty that conforms to the shape of its container, will likely free up a lot of my time. Instead of trying to solve the puzzle. I can spend energy on finding the container that makes me happy&hellip; for the moment.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Ambition Gap - Leaning In]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/the-ambition-gap-lean-in/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-23T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/the-ambition-gap-lean-in</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I may be a little late to the game, but I am finally reading Sheryl Sandberg&rsquo;s &ldquo;Lean In&rdquo;, and right from the introduction I can understand why it caused such a stir when it came out in 2012. Sandberg addresses the issue of why there are relatively few women in leadership roles, and ways that women have held themselves back.<!--more--> Women earn more than 57% of undergraduate degrees and 60% of masters degrees, and yet hold less than 14% of C level positions. I always assumed that as women disproportionately fill the ranks of entry level positions, there would be a proportional increase of women filling senior level positions as well. Apparently this is not the case. &ldquo;The exodus of highly educated women is a major contributor to the leadership gap.&rdquo;</p>

<p><span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='36% of men want to reach the C-suite and only 18% of women.'>
Sandberg shares a story about a kindergarten class where the students were asked &ldquo;What do you want to be when you grow up?&rdquo;. Several of the boys wanted to be president, but none of the girls did. This disparity continues into middle school, where more boys than girls aspire to leadership roles in future careers. 36% of men want to reach the C-suite and only 18% of women. Why so few? If the question were ever posed to me I would honestly say that rising to the C-levels has never been of any interest, and I think Sandberg is right to ask why.
</span></p>

<h3>Too much Barbie or not enough Hillary?</h3>

<p>Sandberg is quick to link the relative derth of women in leadership roles on the messages of obedience and passivity we instill in girls and the general indulgence of opposite traits in boys (&ldquo;boys will be boys&rdquo;). &ldquo;Gender stereotypes introduced in childhood are reinforced throughout our lives and become self-fulfilling prophesies.&rdquo; While gender stereotypes have held women back in the past, today the difference is in their perceived options, not in perceived abilities. When the kindergarten-ers in Sandberg&rsquo;s story were asked what they wanted to be when they grew up they looked to the immediate role models around them. Call it a lack of imagination about one&rsquo;s future career, rather than a lack of ambition.</p>

<p>She has recently begun a campaign to <a href="http://banbossy.com/">ban the word &ldquo;bossy&rdquo;</a>, and while words have the power to shape our values, it is a passive approach to solving the problem. Boys don&rsquo;t show a propensity towards leadership in middle-school any more than girls show a propensity towards secretarial work. Sandberg&rsquo;s <a href="http://leanin.org/">&ldquo;Lean In&rdquo;</a> project comes closer to directly addressing the issue. She realizes that you can&rsquo;t be what you can&rsquo;t see&#8221;, and works to raise the profiles of powerful women. When it becomes normal to have female leaders, I am sure we will find more girls expressing ambition. Likewise, when it becomes normal for men to share equally in care-giving, boys will begin making different choices.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Lean-In-Women-Work-Will/dp/0385349947/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1395756488&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=lean+in">Lean In: Women, Work, and the Will to Lead</a> by Sheryl Sandberg</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Line, Spline]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/line-spline/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/line-spline</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>D3 lines are rendered using linear interpolation by default. This means that the line connecting a series of points will trace a direct path from one node to another:</p>

<div id="graph-here">
  <script src="http://mbostock.github.com/d3/d3.v2.min.js"></script>
  <script>
var width = 400,
    height = 400,
    margin = 5,
    scalex = d3.scale.linear().domain([0, 7]).range([margin, width - margin]),
    scaley = d3.scale.linear().domain([0, 7]).range([height - margin, margin]);

var data = [
  [
      {x: 0, y: 5},{x: 1, y: 7},{x: 2, y: 5},
      {x: 3, y: 5},{x: 4, y: 3},{x: 6, y: 4},
      {x: 7, y: 2}
  ],
  [
      {x: 0, y: 3},{x: 1, y: 5},{x: 2, y: 3},
      {x: 3, y: 3},{x: 4, y: 1},{x: 6, y: 2},
      {x: 7, y: 1}
  ]
];

var straightLine = d3.svg.line()
        .interpolate("linear")
        .x(function(d){return scalex(d.x);})
        .y(function(d){return scaley(d.y);});
var smoothLine = d3.svg.line()
        .interpolate("cardinal")
        .x(function(d){return scalex(d.x);})
        .y(function(d){return scaley(d.y);});

var svg = d3.select("#graph-here").append("svg");

  svg.attr("height", height)
      .attr("width", width);

   svg.selectAll("path")
        .data(data)
      .enter()
        .append("path")
        .attr("class", "line")
        .attr("fill", "none")
        .attr("stroke", "blue")
        .attr("stroke-width", 2)
        .attr("d", function(d, i){
          if(i % 2 === 0) return straightLine(d);
          return smoothLine(d)
        });

    svg.selectAll("textPath").data(data)
      .enter()
        .append("text")
        .attr("x", function(d) { return scalex(d[d.length-2].x); })
        .attr("y", function(d) { return scaley(d[d.length-2].y); })
        .attr("text-anchor", "end")
        .text(function(d, i) {
          if(i % 2 === 0) return "Straight Lines";
          return "Smooth Lines";
        });

  </script>
</div>


<p>The curved line is rendered with the cardinal interpolator, one of several options D3 provides. The curvature of the line is called a <strong>spline</strong>. Splines are tools used by architects to draw curved lines, and the term was adopted by mathematicians to describe smooth, piecewise polynomial approximation:</p>

<blockquote><p>Splines are curves, which are usually required to be continuous and smooth&hellip; [The] join points are called knots. Splines with few knots are generally smoother than splines with many knots; however, increasing the number of knots usually increases the fit of the spline function to the data. Knots give the curve freedom to bend to more closely follow the data. &mdash;<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spline_(mathematics">Wikipedia</a>)</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Multiple Remotes]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/multiple-remotes/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/multiple-remotes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Somehow I had worked out in my head that there could be only one remote. Origin. Turns out you can set and push to a (presumably) infinite number of remote repositories <!--more-->:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Checkout your git config </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>$ git config --list
</span><span class='line'>push.default=nothing
</span><span class='line'>alias.hist=log --pretty=format:"%h %ad | %s%d [%an]" --graph --date=short
</span><span class='line'>user.name=Katie Leonard
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>remote.origin.url=git@github.com:keighty/thorfiles.git
</span><span class='line'>remote.origin.fetch=+refs/heads/*:refs/remotes/origin/*
</span><span class='line'>branch.master.remote=origin
</span><span class='line'>branch.master.merge=refs/heads/master</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>(On a side note, I am not sure I remember putting <code>alias.hist</code> in my git config, but I find it to be wickedly useful.)</p>

<p>Setting a new remote is as easy as:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>1 2 3 a b c </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>$ git remote add new_destination git@github.com:otheruser/thorfiles.git</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Standing back to admire the results:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Simple, but does it work? </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>$ git config --list
</span><span class='line'>push.default=nothing
</span><span class='line'>alias.hist=log --pretty=format:"%h %ad | %s%d [%an]" --graph --date=short
</span><span class='line'>user.name=Katie Leonard
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>remote.origin.url=git@github.com:keighty/thorfiles.git
</span><span class='line'>remote.origin.fetch=+refs/heads/*:refs/remotes/origin/*
</span><span class='line'>branch.master.remote=origin
</span><span class='line'>branch.master.merge=refs/heads/master
</span><span class='line'>remote.new_destination.url=git@github.com:otheruser/thorfiles.git
</span><span class='line'>remote.new_destination.fetch=+refs/heads/*:refs/remotes/new_destination/*</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Fast-forward through some excellent and brilliant feature work on <code>my_branch</code>, and I naturally want to save it for posterity:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Chizeled in metal on GitHub servers </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>$ git push origin my_branch
</span><span class='line'>Counting objects: 611, done.
</span><span class='line'>Delta compression using up to 4 threads.
</span><span class='line'>Compressing objects: 100% (263/263), done.
</span><span class='line'>Writing objects: 100% (375/375), 63.40 KiB | 0 bytes/s, done.
</span><span class='line'>Total 375 (delta 280), reused 189 (delta 105)
</span><span class='line'>To git@github.com:keighty/thorfiles.git
</span><span class='line'> * [new branch]      my_branch -> my_branch</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>I can also share it with my friend&rsquo;s repo, presuming I have write access, and knowing full well he will want to use my new feature:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Update your friends! </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>$ git push new_destination my_branch
</span><span class='line'>Counting objects: 611, done.
</span><span class='line'>Delta compression using up to 4 threads.
</span><span class='line'>Compressing objects: 100% (263/263), done.
</span><span class='line'>Writing objects: 100% (375/375), 63.40 KiB | 0 bytes/s, done.
</span><span class='line'>Total 375 (delta 280), reused 189 (delta 105)
</span><span class='line'>To git@github.com:otheruser/thorfiles.git
</span><span class='line'> * [new branch]      my_branch -> my_branch</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Git is so awesome.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Delay Chained Transitions]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/delay-chained-transitions/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-15T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/delay-chained-transitions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Changing an element using multiple, chained transitions requires a little troubleshooting. You would think that just chaining them one after another would suffice:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Chained Transitions </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='js'><span class='line'><span class="nx">selection</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">transition</span><span class="p">().</span><span class="nx">duration</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1500</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">attr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;cx&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="nx">getX</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">attr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;cy&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="nx">getY</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">attr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;r&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">getR</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">style</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;fill&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">getColor</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">transition</span><span class="p">().</span><span class="nx">duration</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1500</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">attr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;r&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">doubleR</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>But D3 does not wait for one transition to be complete before it begins the next one. Adding a delay will accomplish the desired transition chaining:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>ACTUAL Chained Transitions</span><a href='https://gist.github.com/keighty/9508948'>Gist </a></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='js'><span class='line'><span class="nx">selection</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">transition</span><span class="p">().</span><span class="nx">duration</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1500</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">attr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;cx&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="nx">getX</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">attr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;cy&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="nx">getY</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">attr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;r&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">getR</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">style</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;fill&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">getColor</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">transition</span><span class="p">().</span><span class="nx">delay</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1700</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="nx">duration</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1500</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">attr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;r&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">doubleR</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>




<div id="showme">
<style>
.axis path,
.axis line {
    fill: none;
    stroke: black;
    shape-rendering: crispEdges;
}

.axis text {
    font-family: sans-serif;
    font-size: 11px;
}
</style>
<script src="http://mbostock.github.com/d3/d3.v2.min.js"></script>
<script>

var width = 500,
    height = 500,
    margin = 50,
    data,
    dataFromCsv;

var scaleX=d3.scale.linear().domain([0,10]).range([margin,width-margin]);
var scaleY=d3.scale.linear().domain([0,10]).range([height-margin,margin]);

var svg=d3.select("#showme").append("svg")
      .attr("width",width)
      .attr("height",height);

function drawAxes() {
  var xAxis = d3.svg.axis()
    .scale(scaleX)
    .orient("bottom")
    .ticks(5)
    .tickSubdivide(1)
    .tickPadding(10)
    .tickFormat(function(d) { return d + " ticks"});

  var yAxis = d3.svg.axis()
    .scale(scaleY)
    .orient("left");

  svg.append("g")
    .attr("class", "axis")
    .attr("transform", "translate(0," + (height - margin) + ")")
    .call(xAxis);
  svg.append("text")
    .attr("class", "x label")
    .attr("text-anchor", "middle")
    .attr("x", width/2)
    .attr("y", height)
    .text("X-value");

  svg.append("g")
    .attr("class", "axis")
    .attr("transform", "translate(" + margin + ",0)")
    .call(yAxis);
  svg.append("text")
    .attr("class", "y label")
    .attr("text-anchor", "middle")
    .attr("x", -height/2)
    .attr("y", 6)
    .attr("dy", ".75em")
    .attr("transform", "rotate(-90)")
    .text("Y-value");
}

dataFromCsv = [{ "Color": "#9467bd", "X": 1, "Y": 8, "Quantity": 91 },
{ "Color": "#1f77b4", "X": 9, "Y": 1, "Quantity": 32 },
{ "Color": "#1f77b4", "X": 3, "Y": 1, "Quantity": 67 },
{ "Color": "#bcbd22", "X": 5, "Y": 5, "Quantity": 63 },
{ "Color": "#9467bd", "X": 6, "Y": 6, "Quantity": 57 },
{ "Color": "#2ca02c", "X": 5, "Y": 10, "Quantity": 65 },
{ "Color": "#d62728", "X": 8, "Y": 2, "Quantity": 36 },
{ "Color": "#9467bd", "X": 2, "Y": 8, "Quantity": 82 },
{ "Color": "#bcbd22", "X": 4, "Y": 7, "Quantity": 69 },
{ "Color": "#9467bd", "X": 5, "Y": 3, "Quantity": 88 },
{ "Color": "#d62728", "X": 1, "Y": 5, "Quantity": 29 },
{ "Color": "#1f77b4", "X": 10, "Y": 7, "Quantity": 60 },
{ "Color": "#2ca02c", "X": 8, "Y": 5, "Quantity": 56 },
{ "Color": "#bcbd22", "X": 1, "Y": 6, "Quantity": 31 },
{ "Color": "#bcbd22", "X": 6, "Y": 5, "Quantity": 57 },
{ "Color": "#d62728", "X": 9, "Y": 6, "Quantity": 85 },
{ "Color": "indigo", "X": 9, "Y": 10, "Quantity": 70 },
{ "Color": "indigo", "X": 9, "Y": 10, "Quantity": 31 },
{ "Color": "#1f77b4", "X": 2, "Y": 4, "Quantity": 26 },
{ "Color": "#bcbd22", "X": 10, "Y": 5, "Quantity": 61 },
{ "Color": "#2ca02c", "X": 4, "Y": 2, "Quantity": 64 },
{ "Color": "#1f77b4", "X": 8, "Y": 9, "Quantity": 71 }];
function importData() {
  data = d3.nest()
          .key(function(d) { return d.Color; })
          .rollup(aggregateData)
          .entries(dataFromCsv);
  // drawElements();
  setInterval( drawElements, 4000 );
}

/***********************
  Draw circles, bind data, and move elements to final location
***********************/
function drawElements() {
  var selection = svg.selectAll("circle").data(data);

  selection.enter()
    .append("circle")
    .attr("cx",scaleX(0))
    .attr("cy",scaleY(0))
    .attr("r", 0)

  selection.transition().duration(1500)
      .attr("cx",getX)
      .attr("cy",getY)
      .attr("r", getR)
      .style("fill", getColor)
    .transition().delay(1500+200).duration(1500)
      .attr("r", doubleR);
}

/***********************
  Helper functions
***********************/
function getX(d)     { return scaleX(d.values.X); }
function getY(d)     { return scaleY(d.values.Y); }
function getR(d)     { return d.values.Quantity / 10; }
function doubleR(d)     { return d.values.Quantity / 5; }
function getColor(d) { return d.key; }
// Use D3 built in array functions to aggregate data
function aggregateData(d) {
  return {
    "X"       : d3.mean(d, function(e) { return +e.X; }),
    "Y"       : d3.median(d, function(e) { return +e.Y; }),
    "Quantity": d3.max(d, function(e) { return +e.Quantity; })
  };
}

drawAxes();
importData();
</script>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Easing Does It]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/easing-does-it/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/easing-does-it</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With the possible exception of UFOs, things don&rsquo;t usually switch from being stationary to moving at maximum velocity without an intervening period of acceleration or deceleration. Similarly, it can be difficult to track elements on a web page that move from one position to another with no warning, or faster than the human eye can perceive. Enter easing functions: <!--more--></p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;<strong>Easing functions</strong> specify the rate of change of a parameter over time.&rdquo; &mdash;Robert Penner</p></blockquote>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Easy easing</span><a href='https://gist.github.com/keighty/9508948'>Gist </a></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='js'><span class='line'><span class="nx">selection</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">enter</span><span class="p">()</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">append</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;circle&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">attr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;cx&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="nx">scaleX</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">))</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">attr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;cy&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="nx">scaleY</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">))</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">attr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;r&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nx">selection</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">transition</span><span class="p">().</span><span class="nx">ease</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;cubic-in-out&quot;</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="nx">duration</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1500</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">attr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;cx&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="nx">getX</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">attr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;cy&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="nx">getY</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">attr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;r&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">getR</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">style</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;fill&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">getColor</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>The transition will act on the selection in the following ways:</p>

<ul>
<li>it will move the element from its starting x position of 0 to the x position defined by <code>getX()</code></li>
<li>it will move the element from its starting y position of 0 to the y position defined by <code>getY()</code></li>
<li>it will increase the element&rsquo;s radius from 0 to the radius returned from <code>getR()</code></li>
<li>it will gradually change the element&rsquo;s color using an ordinal color scale, from black to the color returned from <code>getColor()</code></li>
<li>all of this movement will be performed with a &ldquo;cubic-in-out&rdquo; easing function</li>
</ul>


<p>The cubic-in-out easing function is the standard D3 easing function. The element will increase velocity by a power of 3 until halfway down the path it is destined to trace. It will then decrease velocity by a power of 3 until it reaches its final location. There are many different types of easing functions. Check out the resources for more information, and ask your doctor which easing function is right for you!</p>

<h3>Resources</h3>

<p>Robert Penner&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.robertpenner.com/easing/">Easing Functions</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/178216216X/ref=as_li_tf_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=178216216X&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=bridgeforpoke-20">Data Visualization with D3.js Cookbook</a> (affiliate link)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Value of Slow Transitions]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/the-value-of-transition/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-08T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/the-value-of-transition</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>The Why</h3>

<p>From <a href="http://bost.ocks.org/mike/constancy/">Object Constancy</a> by Mike Bostock:</p>

<blockquote><p>Animated transitions are pretty, but they also serve a purpose: they make it easier to follow the data. This is known as <strong>object constancy</strong>: a graphical element that represents a particular data point&hellip; can be tracked visually through the transition. This lessens the cognitive burden by using <strong>preattentive processing</strong> of motion rather than sequential scanning of labels.</p></blockquote>

<p>(The emphasis is mine)</p>

<h3>The How</h3>

<p>Object constancy is achieved through object identity: the data is bound to it&rsquo;s object by a shared unique identifier. This allows D3 to reuse the object when the data set is updated. Object identity is achieved by passing a key function to the data() method at the time of data binding:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>var data = [ // &lt;-A
</span><span class='line'>        {id: 0, value: "foo"},
</span><span class='line'>        {id: 1, value: "bar"},
</span><span class='line'>        {id: 2, value: "foo"},
</span><span class='line'>        {id: 3, value: "baz"},
</span><span class='line'>        {id: 4, value: "bar"}
</span><span class='line'>    ];
</span><span class='line'>d3.selectAll("svg:g")
</span><span class='line'>    .data(data, function(d){return d.id;});</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Git, What Have I Done?]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/git-what-have-i-done/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-08T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/git-what-have-i-done</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Git, the superhero of version control, allows you to review all the commands that have modified the HEAD tag in a git repo: <code>git reflog</code></p>

<p>The output for one of my demo apps:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Git, you&#8217;re my hero </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'>5075d26 HEAD@<span class="o">{</span>0<span class="o">}</span>: checkout: moving from master to kleonard/add_skyline_background
</span><span class='line'>531c396 HEAD@<span class="o">{</span>1<span class="o">}</span>: pull: fast forward
</span><span class='line'>435f6de HEAD@<span class="o">{</span>2<span class="o">}</span>: commit: Adds logic <span class="k">for </span>running and testing
</span><span class='line'>043e35a HEAD@<span class="o">{</span>3<span class="o">}</span>: commit: Adds logic to process input
</span><span class='line'>5155ba4 HEAD@<span class="o">{</span>4<span class="o">}</span>: commit: Adds input file
</span><span class='line'>a629871 HEAD@<span class="o">{</span>5<span class="o">}</span>: rebase finished: returning to refs/heads/kleonard/create_input_files
</span><span class='line'>a010021 HEAD@<span class="o">{</span>6<span class="o">}</span>: rebase: Add input file
</span><span class='line'>b7cd86a HEAD@<span class="o">{</span>7<span class="o">}</span>: commit: Initial commit arbitrage
</span><span class='line'>5ed00ea HEAD@<span class="o">{</span>8<span class="o">}</span>: commit: Adds launcher
</span><span class='line'>7b2d720 HEAD@<span class="o">{</span>9<span class="o">}</span>: commit: Adds logic to find smallest number of moves
</span><span class='line'>9c0dfce HEAD@<span class="o">{</span>10<span class="o">}</span>: commit: Adds implementation <span class="k">for </span>bin creation
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Hmmm&hellip; looks like my commit messages need a little work&hellip; Still, it is a great tool for catching up on the changes to a repo (especially if you haven&rsquo;t touched it in a while), finding out where the bulk of the work is happening, or just reminding yourself what you did yesterday.</p>

<p>Awesome.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Transition With Style]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/transition-with-style/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-06T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/transition-with-style</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Making things zoom across the page is what I used to think javascript was all about, but it wasn&rsquo;t until I started learning d3 that I found out how to make it happen.</p>

<!--more-->




<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Simple Transition </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='js'><span class='line'><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">body</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">d3</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">select</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;body&quot;</span><span class="p">),</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">duration</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">2000</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nx">body</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">append</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;div&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">style</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;background-color&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s2">&quot;white&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">style</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;margin&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s2">&quot;40px&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">style</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;width&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s2">&quot;200px&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">style</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;height&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s2">&quot;200px&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">style</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;border&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s2">&quot;black solid thin&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">transition</span><span class="p">()</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">duration</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">duration</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">style</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;background-color&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s2">&quot;black&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">style</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;margin-left&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s2">&quot;600px&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">style</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;width&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s2">&quot;100px&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">style</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;height&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s2">&quot;100px&quot;</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>D3 is smart enough to select an appropriate scale for the property in transition. If a transitioning element is not given an explicit starting point, D3 will use the computed style. If the end value is missing, the property will be treated as a constant. In the example above, the border stays the same, as do the top and bottom margins. The only properties that change are the ones specified below the transition().</p>

<p>Awesome.</p>

<h3>Resources</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/178216216X/ref=as_li_tf_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=178216216X&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=bridgeforpoke-20">Data Visualization with D3.js Cookbook</a> (affiliate link)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fun With Ticks]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/scales-and-ticks/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-05T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/scales-and-ticks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>D3 has an awesome tick library, which makes it easy to customize an axis. I have not found any evidence of a built in function to customize tick rendering depending on if it is a major or a minor tick. One way to get around that is to render two axes, and only label one<!--more-->:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>axes ticks </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
<span class='line-number'>21</span>
<span class='line-number'>22</span>
<span class='line-number'>23</span>
<span class='line-number'>24</span>
<span class='line-number'>25</span>
<span class='line-number'>26</span>
<span class='line-number'>27</span>
<span class='line-number'>28</span>
<span class='line-number'>29</span>
<span class='line-number'>30</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='js'><span class='line'><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">scaleX</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="nx">d3</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">scale</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">linear</span><span class="p">().</span><span class="nx">domain</span><span class="p">([</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">10</span><span class="p">]).</span><span class="nx">range</span><span class="p">([</span><span class="nx">margin</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="nx">width</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="nx">margin</span><span class="p">]);</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">svg</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="nx">d3</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">select</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;body&quot;</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="nx">append</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;svg&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">attr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;width&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="nx">width</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">attr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;height&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="nx">height</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">xAxis</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">d3</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">svg</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">axis</span><span class="p">()</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">scale</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">scaleX</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">orient</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;bottom&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">ticks</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">5</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">tickSubdivide</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">5</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">tickPadding</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">10</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">tickFormat</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">d</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="k">return</span> <span class="nx">d</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="s2">&quot; ticks&quot;</span><span class="p">});</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">x2Axis</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">d3</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">svg</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">axis</span><span class="p">()</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">scale</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">scaleX</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">orient</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;bottom&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">ticks</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">5</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">tickSize</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">14</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">tickFormat</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;&quot;</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nx">svg</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">append</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;g&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">attr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;class&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s2">&quot;axis&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">attr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;transform&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s2">&quot;translate(0,&quot;</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">margin</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="s2">&quot;)&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">call</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">xAxis</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nx">svg</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">append</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;g&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">attr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;class&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s2">&quot;axis&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">attr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;transform&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s2">&quot;translate(0,&quot;</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">margin</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="s2">&quot;)&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">call</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">x2Axis</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>TADA</h3>

<p><img src="http://www.katieleonard.ca/images/post_d3_scale_major_ticks.png"></p>

<h3>More fun with ticks</h3>

<ul>
<li><strong>orient()</strong>: set which side of the axis will be ticked and labeled</li>
<li><strong>ticks()</strong>: set the number of major ticks</li>
<li><strong>tickSubdivide()</strong>: set the number of minor ticks</li>
<li><strong>tickPadding()</strong>: set the distance between the ticks and their label</li>
<li><strong>tickFormat()</strong>: set the units to appear after the label on the major ticks</li>
<li><strong>tickSize()</strong>: specify one arg for inner ticks, another argument for outer ticks, or use outerTickSize() or innerTickSize() to specify one or the other. Outer ticks are at the ends of the scales.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[D3 Nests and Rollups]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/d3-nests-and-rollups/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-04T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/d3-nests-and-rollups</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>D3 provides powerful functions for manipulating raw data sets, including csv(), nest(), and rollup().</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I generated a hundred rows of test_data.csv using <a href="http://www.generatedata.com/#about">generatedata.com</a>:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>test_data.csv</span><a href='https://gist.github.com/keighty/9348444#file-test_data-csv'>Gist </a></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'>Colors,X,Y,Quantity
</span><span class='line'>violet,1,8,91
</span><span class='line'>blue,9,1,32
</span><span class='line'>blue,3,1,67
</span><span class='line'>yellow,5,5,63
</span><span class='line'>violet,6,6,57
</span><span class='line'>green,5,10,65
</span><span class='line'>red,8,2,36
</span><span class='line'>...
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>The basic properties are a Color (one of blue, yellow, violet, green, and red), an X-value (between 1 and 10), a Y-value (also between 1 and 10), and a Quantity value (between 1 and 100).</p>

<h3>csv()</h3>

<p>You can import a raw, comma-delimited data file, and bind the data directly to an svg.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>csv()</span><a href='https://gist.github.com/keighty/9348444'>Gist </a></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='js'><span class='line'><span class="nx">d3</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">csv</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;test_data.csv&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">csv</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">svg</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">selectAll</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;circle&quot;</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="nx">data</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">csv</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="nx">enter</span><span class="p">()</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">append</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;circle&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">attr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;cx&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="nx">getX</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">attr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;cy&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="nx">getY</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">attr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;r&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">getR</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">style</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;fill&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">getColor</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">})</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p><img src="http://www.katieleonard.ca/images/post_d3_csv_data.png"></p>

<h3>nest() and rollup()</h3>

<p>You can also aggregate data on any property &mdash; just tell D3 which one, and use any of D3&rsquo;s handy utility functions (mean, median, sum, min/max, quantile, etc) to return the aggregate data you want to display. For example, I want to plot the average data for each color. I tell my D3 selection to nest the data on the color key. Then I tell the rollup function to take the average for each property of the data. Pass the new data to the svg instead of the csv, and voila</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>nest() and rollup()</span><a href='https://gist.github.com/keighty/9348540'>Gist </a></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='js'><span class='line'><span class="nx">d3</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">csv</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;test_data.csv&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">csv</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">data</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">d3</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">nest</span><span class="p">()</span>
</span><span class='line'>          <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">key</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">d</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="k">return</span> <span class="nx">d</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">Colors</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="p">})</span>
</span><span class='line'>          <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">rollup</span><span class="p">(</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">d</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>            <span class="k">return</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>              <span class="s2">&quot;X&quot;</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="nx">d3</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">mean</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">d</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="k">return</span> <span class="o">+</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">X</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="p">}),</span>
</span><span class='line'>              <span class="s2">&quot;Y&quot;</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="nx">d3</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">mean</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">d</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="k">return</span> <span class="o">+</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">Y</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="p">}),</span>
</span><span class='line'>              <span class="s2">&quot;Quantity&quot;</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="nx">d3</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">mean</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">d</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="k">return</span> <span class="o">+</span><span class="nx">e</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">Quantity</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="p">})</span>
</span><span class='line'>            <span class="p">};</span>
</span><span class='line'>          <span class="p">})</span>
</span><span class='line'>          <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">entries</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">csv</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">svg</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">selectAll</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;circle&quot;</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="nx">data</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">data</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="nx">enter</span><span class="p">()</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">append</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;circle&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">attr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;cx&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="nx">getX</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">attr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;cy&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="nx">getY</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">attr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;r&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">getR</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">style</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;fill&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">getColor</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">})</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p><img src="http://www.katieleonard.ca/images/post_d3_rollupdata_image.png"></p>

<p>D3 is so awesome.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Technique for Producing Ideas]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/a-technique-for-producing-ideas/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-04T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/a-technique-for-producing-ideas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B001C34HUS/ref=as_li_tf_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=B001C34HUS&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=bridgeforpoke-20">A Technique for Producing Ideas</a> by James Webb Young (1965)</p>

<p>Young proposes that all ideas are the result of five identifiable stages of rumination, whether they are followed consciously or not:</p>

<ol>
<li>Gather information, and not just what is specific to your problem domain. Novelty comes from mashing seemingly unrelated concepts together.</li>
<li>Review the information &mdash; collate your information in some fashion and go over it. A lot.</li>
<li>Do something else. Get distracted from whatever problem you are trying to solve.</li>
<li>&ldquo;Eureka! I have it!&rdquo;</li>
<li>Refine your idea &mdash; first drafts are never perfect, so keep polishing.</li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
