<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Read | keighty]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/categories/read/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-06T20:01:52-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[katie leonard]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Slack]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/slack/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-03T08:06:13-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/slack</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0932633617/ref=as_li_tf_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=0932633617&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=bridgeforpoke-20">Slack</a>: Getting Past Burnout, Busywork and the Myth of Total Efficiency by Tom DeMarco</p>

<p>Surround your pullquote like this {" text to be quoted "}</p>

<p>Slack is essential for adapting to change.
 &ldquo;The more highly adapted an organism becomes, the less adaptable it is to any new change.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Knowledge work
 &ndash; non fungible
 &ndash; high cost of task switching</p>

<p>Importance of failure
 &ndash; a culture of learning
 &ndash; without fear of making mistakes
 &ndash; &ldquo;Risk avoidance is flight from opportunity&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;Slack is the natural enemy of efficiency, and efficiency is the natural enemy of slack.&rdquo;</p>

<p>fungible: being of such nature or kind as to be freely exchangeable or replaceable, in whole or in part, for another of like nature or kind</p>

<p>&ldquo;immersion time is required to overcome a kind of metal inertia&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;People under time pressure don&rsquo;t think faster&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;shouldn&rsquo;t do any kind of error-prone work late in a work session, because they know their thinking is no longer sufficiently clear for that kind of task&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;The safety that is required for essential change is a sure sense that no one will be mocked, demeaned, or belittled while struggling to achieve renewed mastery.&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;the essense of the training experience is this slowing down (Learning takes time.)&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;We grew up in an age where stasis was a possibility and a desired state. Change was something you went through to reach a new and better stasis.&rdquo;</p>

<!--more-->

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
