<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Read | keighty]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/categories/read/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/"/>
  <updated>2016-12-10T11:10:49-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[katie leonard]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[keighty.leonard@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Estimate != Commitment != Target]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2015/software-estimation-is-hard/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-31T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2015/software-estimation-is-hard</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Software estimation is hard, but I didn&rsquo;t really understand why until I started reading <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Software-Estimation-Demystifying-Developer-Practices/dp/0735605351">Software Estimation: Demystifying the Black Art</a> by Steve McConnell. It was published in 2006, and is very much still relevant &mdash; there are more ways to do estimation wrong than to do it right.</p>

<p>The biggest &ldquo;aha&rdquo; moment for me was learning the difference between estimates, targets, and commitments. <!--more-->I always thought that estimates were commitments and treated them like targets. If a task took longer than my estimate, I would worry that I had blown the project plan. The source of my stress was really semantics, and a deep misunderstanding of project plans in general.</p>

<h4>1. An estimate is a range where there is a 90% chance of finding the completion date</h4>

<p>An estimate is not a single point in time &mdash; that is a target. There is uncertainty in software development, and uncertainty about the uncertainty.</p>

<blockquote><p>There is a limit to how well a project can go but no limit to how many problems can occur.</p></blockquote>

<p>Estimates are probability distrubutions of possible outcomes:</p>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/151031-software-estimation/estimation-chart.png"></p>

<p>Most of my experience in estimating projects has been to break a feature down into small tasks and estimate those. Tightly defined requirements for a task make it easier to estimate, but there are always complications that can throw things off track. Thinking about an estimate as a range of possibilities between the best and worst case scenarios reduces stress about being right the first time.</p>

<h4>2. A commitment is a promise to deliver defined functionality at a certain level of quality at a certain date.</h4>

<p>You can use estimates to plan commitments, but not the other way around. If ten features take a year to develop, but your customer needs to have something in six months, you can commit to delivering four or five features by that target, but there is no way you can deliver ten.</p>

<h4>3. A target is a single point in time, and is usually determined by business needs.</h4>

<p>A target has more in common with a commitment than an estimate &mdash; it can have no bearing on the time estimated to complete a project, but will often define the envelope of time. Like in the previous example, the target for delivery to the customer was six months, but the commitment could be four or five features, depending on the estimates for each feature.</p>

<p>Estimation must come before planning, and before you really understand all of the requirements for the project. More often than not, events that happen during the project will have a big impact on the assumptions made to estimate the project at the beginning. Estimates are hard, but McConnell has some awesome advice on how to get it right.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Clean Coder]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2015/the-clean-coder/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-26T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2015/the-clean-coder</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Clean-Coder-Conduct-Professional-Programmers/dp/0137081073/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1443288322&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+clean+coder">The Clean Coder: A Code of Conduct for Professional Programmers</a>, Bob Martin (Uncle Bob) tells you what it means to be a professional programmer. Much of what distinguishes a professional from a non-professional can be reduced to responsibility: a professional is responsible for their project, their team, and their own career. <!--more--></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Clean-Coder-Conduct-Professional-Programmers/dp/0137081073/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1443288322&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+clean+coder"><img class="left" src="/images/150926-clean-coder/cleancoder.jpg"></a></p>

<h2>Protect your projects</h2>

<p>Your first responsibility, according to Uncle Bob, is to your employer, which means doing the job that you have been hired to do.</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Make reasonable estimates.</strong> Your project does not exist in isolation from other parts of the company. An estimate is a probability distribution of likely outcomes, not a single point in time. Many stakeholders rely on your estimates for coordinating marketing, sales, and other downstream tasks.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Meet your commitments.</strong> Estimates are different from commitments. If you have committed to delivering a feature or a product by a target date, meet that date.</p></li>
</ul>


<blockquote><p>If it can&rsquo;t be done, you can still commit to actions that will bring you closer to the target. Finding out if it can be done can be one of the actions to commit to!</p></blockquote>

<ul>
<li><strong>Protect your time.</strong> An easy way to ensure the success of your project is to devote the time and energy you have already promised in your estimates. Meetings can be disruptive to your workflow, and you should decline any meeting that does not move your project forward. If you can&rsquo;t decline, ask for an agenda and clear goals before you accept.</li>
</ul>


<blockquote><p>Sometimes the meeting will be about something that interests you, but is not immediately necessary. You will have to choose whether you can afford the time. Be careful — there may be more than enough of these meetings to consume your days.</p></blockquote>

<h2>Protect your team</h2>

<blockquote><p>A team-player communicates frequently, keeps an eye out for his or her teammates, and executes his or her own responsibilities as well as possible.</p></blockquote>

<ul>
<li><strong>Stand by your original estimates</strong>, and don&rsquo;t confuse them with commitments. Your estimates should protect your team from long hours, undue management pressure, and unpleasant surprises. Don&rsquo;t promise what your team can&rsquo;t deliver.</li>
</ul>


<blockquote><p>Business likes to view estimates as commitments. Developers like to view estimates as guesses. The difference is profound.</p></blockquote>

<ul>
<li><strong>Mentor less experienced engineers.</strong> Contributing to the growth of everyone will make your team stronger. Don&rsquo;t wear your headphones to cut yourself off from interruptions. Making yourself available as a resource will get someone else on the team unstuck, which moves your project forward (Uncle Bob recommends using TDD instead of the Zone to pick up the stack if you have to drop it). “It is unprofessional to be a loner or a recluse on a team."</li>
</ul>


<h2>Protect your career</h2>

<p>Your employer is not responsible for keeping your skills up to date. They are not required to ensure that you are aware of cutting edge technologies and languages.</p>

<blockquote><p>Your career is your responsibility. It is not your employer&rsquo;s responsibility to make sure you are marketable. It is not your employer&rsquo;s responsibility to train you, or to send you to conferences, or to buy you books. These things are your responsibility. Woe to the software developer who entrusts his career to his employer.</p></blockquote>

<ul>
<li><strong>Practice coding.</strong> Uncle Bob is a big proponent of practicing code. Performing code kata before starting work will put you in the right frame of mind.</li>
</ul>


<blockquote><p>Professionals practice. True professionals work hard to keep their skills sharp and ready. It is not enough to simply do your daily job and call that practice. Doing your job is daily performance, not practice. Practice is when you specifically exercise your skills outside of the performance of your job for the sole purpose of refining and enhancing those skills.</p></blockquote>

<ul>
<li><strong>Learn about the industry.</strong> Falling behind in new technologies will make you obsolete. You will not stay marketable to new employers (or even your current employer), if you do not stay current.</li>
</ul>


<p>Reading The Clean Coder was like sitting down with a mentor and asking how I can grow my career. I would recommend it for anyone entering the profession today!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bird by Bird]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2015/bird-by-bird/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2015/bird-by-bird</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Virtue is its own reward, and so is writing. Anne Lamott&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Bird-Some-Instructions-Writing-Life/dp/0385480016/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1425241344&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=bird+by+bird">Bird by Bird: Some Instructions on Writing and Life</a> is full of beautiful prose, characters, and personal anecdotes, and while her advice is tuned to the creative writer, there are three useful lessons that can be applied to all writing.</p>

<ol>
<li>write short assignments</li>
<li>write only what you can see through a 1-inch picture frame</li>
<li>write a terrible first draft</li>
</ol>


<p>Blogging about what I am learning and reading forces me to think about what I experience. Almost every day I learn another 1-inch picture frame of programming, and writing it down helps me understand it better. My ugly first drafts usually consist of a question, a few links to resources, and some console output &mdash; not Pulitzer Prize winning prose, but an awesome personal resource and record of growth.</p>

<blockquote><p>All you can give us is what life is about from your point of view. You are not going to be able to give us the plans to the submarine. Life is not a submarine. There are no plans.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Everybody Writes (and Why You Should Blog)]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2015/everybody-writes/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-16T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2015/everybody-writes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In <em>Everybody Writes</em><sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, Ann Handley teaches content marketers how to generate &ldquo;ridiculously good&rdquo; content. Anyone who has recently enjoyed the pain of the job hunt will notice that much of the advice can be adapted to self-marketing. In my recent code school experience, developing an online presence was as important as learning web development, and since it is hard to market yourself as a web developer without developing anything for the web, a blog is a great place to start. You have picked a career where your ability to learn is one of your most marketable skills, as well as your ability to communicate &mdash; both of which you can showcase in your blog. You don&rsquo;t have to worry about having something original to say: treat it as an opportunity to organize your thoughts and to teach a beginner what you know. Handley gives great advice for people learning to blog and how to generally optimize your online presence &mdash; both are great ways to market yourself as a fresh code-school alum.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Show up</h3>

<p>Write early, write often. If something is new to you, it will likely be new to someone else as well. The more writing practice you get, the easier it becomes &mdash; &ldquo;writing is a habit, not an art&rdquo;, and you can&rsquo;t help but improve in an art that you practice every day. Handley recommends starting with the ugly first draft<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> &mdash; make it ugly, don&rsquo;t delete anything, don&rsquo;t rephrase or reread. Just get it out of you and on to your screen, then walk away for a day. Maybe two. If you are really stuck on how to begin, you could start with &ldquo;Dear diary&rdquo;<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>. This helps you get in the mood to write, and keeps your tone conversational. Also, if you are writing to a non-technical person, it will keep your writing clear, and inspire you to give enough back story so that they aren&rsquo;t lost.</p>

<h3>Write a tight post</h3>

<h4>Decide on a goal</h4>

<p>Is it to teach? To share? To critique? The goal for technical blogs is not usually to obtain a following &mdash; it is to share a bit of experience that will turn up when another frustrated developer puts keywords into a search engine. An online presence is important, but it should not be a blow by blow of how hard it is to learn to code. A handy formula for creating quality content is:</p>

<blockquote><p>Utility * Inspiration * Empathy = Quality Content<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup></p></blockquote>

<p>Make it useful, make it reader centric (even if that reader is you six months from now), and make it thoughtful.</p>

<h4>Forget the 5 paragraph essay format from high school</h4>

<p>I rarely read a long blog post from beginning to end, and the sweet spot for length is around 1500 words<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup>. Make it easy for the reader to get the gist of your post by providing sub-headings, bold text, and code samples &mdash; these are strong visual elements that can help your reader anchor what they are learning.</p>

<h4>Rewrite</h4>

<p>Once you have written the ugly first draft with your goal in mind, rewrite it with the reader in mind &mdash; will they understand the context of what you are trying to get across? Assume the reader knows nothing, but isn’t stupid. Find data and examples that illustrate what you are trying to share (and make sure that you give credit where credit is due<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" rel="footnote">6</a></sup>).</p>

<h4>Work on your grammar</h4>

<p>After reframing, examine your sentence structure. Are you using a passive voice? Microsoft Word grammar check hates the passive voice, but I never knew what that meant. Try <a href="https://www.grammarly.com/">grammarly</a> if you need help, and even if you think you don&rsquo;t. Editing your own work is hard, because your brain will fill in all the things you meant to say but didn&rsquo;t. Also, put the important words at the start of the sentence, just in case the reader dozes off half-way through.</p>

<h3>About Me pages</h3>

<p>Be intentional about the words that describe you in your About Me page<sup id="fnref:7"><a href="#fn:7" rel="footnote">7</a></sup>. Describe your accomplishments with examples, and if possible, try to mirror the language used by the companies you want to work for. Check out the keywords they use, and make sure to encorporate them in your headlines and personal summary.</p>

<blockquote><p>About us pages aren’t really about the company; instead they focus on relaying who they are <em>in relation to the visitor</em>.</p></blockquote>

<p>If your reader is an employer, let them know you are for hire &mdash; your posts should always be in the context of what you can do for the reader.</p>

<p>Showing up can be the hardest thing &mdash; finding something original to say, or fearing a public mistake is what keeps many people from writing, but blogging shows you are interested in, well, something. Being interesting means being interested in things, and wanting to share the things you find interesting is a natural follow through. Given the right mentorship, your technical abilities will grow, but getting in the door is step one. So, if you are looking to update your web presence, or create a web presence, this book is for you.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Handley, A. (2014). <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Everybody-Writes-Go--Creating-Ridiculously-ebook/dp/B00LMB5P0G/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1424115248&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=everybody+writes"><em>Everybody Writes : Your Go-To Guide to Creating Ridiculously Good Content</em></a>. Wiley &amp; Sons Canada, Limited, John.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Tip 9: &ldquo;Embrace the Ugly First Draft&rdquo;, p. 41.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>Tip 14: &ldquo;Start with <em>Dear Mom&hellip;</em>&rdquo;, p. 54.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>&ldquo;Introduction&rdquo;, p. 7.<a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p>Tip 60: &ldquo;The Ideal Length for Blog Posts, Podcast, Facebook Posts, Tweets, and Other Marketing Content&rdquo;, p. 184.<a href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:6">
<p>Tip 57: &ldquo;Seek Permission, Not Forgiveness&rdquo;, p. 170.<a href="#fnref:6" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:7">
<p>Tip 71: &ldquo;Writing the About Us Page&rdquo;, p 244.<a href="#fnref:7" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Clean Code]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2015/clean-code/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-07T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2015/clean-code</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The book club I belong to has a two-fold mission: the first is to inspire through peer pressure to read (and finish) technical books, and the second is to improve our ability to write quality, maintainable code. We started with <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Practical-Object-Oriented-Design-Ruby-Addison-Wesley/dp/0321721330/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1423423708&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=practical+object-oriented+design+in+ruby"><em>Practical Object Oriented Design in Ruby</em></a> (Sandi Metz), and are now on to <a href="http://www.amazon.com/s/ref=nb_sb_ss_i_0_11?url=search-alias%3Daps&amp;field-keywords=refactoring&amp;sprefix=refactoring%2Caps%2C217"><em>Refactoring</em></a> (Martin Fowler and Kent Beck). Along the way, I found a copy of <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Clean-Code-Handbook-Software-Craftsmanship/dp/0132350882/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1423423781&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=clean+code"><em>Clean Code</em></a> by Robert C. Martin in our work library, and dove right in. These three books tout many of the the same principles but focus on different aspects of writing quality code: POODR teaches how to identify abstractions, and to design decoupled objects; Refactoring is a deep dive into the techniques and heuristics for eliminating common code smells; and Clean Code is the intersection between them. It is a style guide, a call to action, and a cautionary tale from the voices of experience. I had several aha moments while reading Clean Code, and here are a few<!--more-->:</p>

<h3>Error handling</h3>

<p>When I started to anticipate <code>undefined method 'length' for nil:NilClass</code> errors, I knew I was growing as a developer.
Having traced the source of <code>undefined is not a function</code> enough times, I came to realize that I was not sufficiently controlling the messages passing between objects.</p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Could return nil </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">find_a_user</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="vi">@user</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="no">User</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">where</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">last_name</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="n">ldquo</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="no">Bacon</span><span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="n">rdquo</span><span class="p">;)</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">first</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="ss">:find_a_user</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="sr">/p&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="sr">&lt;p&gt;find_a_user</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="sr">@user.last_name&lt;/</span><span class="nb">p</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nb">p</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="ss">NoMethodError</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="n">undefined</span> <span class="nb">method</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">code</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="n">last_name</span><span class="err">&#39;</span> <span class="k">for</span> <span class="kp">nil</span><span class="ss">:NilClass</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">from</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">pry</span><span class="p">):</span><span class="mi">10</span><span class="ss">:in</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="sr">/code&gt;&lt;strong&gt;pry&lt;/s</span><span class="n">trong</span><span class="o">&gt;&amp;</span><span class="n">lsquo</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>This first pass seemed totally reasonable to me &mdash; find a particular user, and return it. Of course, what if the user doesn&rsquo;t exist? What if the query timed out? The code on line 7 is reasonable (wherever it may live), but if <code>@user</code> is set to nil my app will blow up. Surround your pullquote like this {" text to be quoted "}</p>

<blockquote><p>If you are calling a [nil]-returning method from a third-party API, consider wrapping that method with a method that either throws an exception or returns a special case object.</p></blockquote>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Never returns nil </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">find_a_user</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">if</span> <span class="vi">@user</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="no">User</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">where</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">last_name</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="n">ldquo</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="no">Bacon</span><span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="n">rdquo</span><span class="p">;)</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">first</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="sr">/p&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="sr">&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;@user</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="sr">&lt;/</span><span class="n">code</span><span class="o">&gt;&lt;</span><span class="sr">/pre&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="sr">&lt;p&gt;  else&lt;/</span><span class="nb">p</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">pre</span><span class="o">&gt;&lt;</span><span class="n">code</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="k">raise</span> <span class="no">StandardError</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">new</span> <span class="s2">&quot;Could not find Mr. Bacon.&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="sr">/code&gt;&lt;/</span><span class="n">pre</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nb">p</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>  <span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">end</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="sr">/p&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="sr">&lt;p&gt;find_a_user</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="sr">=&gt; StandardError: Could not find Mr. Bacon.</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>Now the error occurs where it belongs &mdash; with the retrieval of the user. Throwing an error when something goes wrong is the least you can do for the consumers of your method. You could also solidify your contract by guaranteeing that you return something they expect.</p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">interesting_things</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="vi">@interesting_things</span> <span class="o">||</span> <span class="o">[]</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">end</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="sr">/p&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="sr">&lt;p&gt;interesting_things.length</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="sr">=&gt; 0</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>I have guaranteed that <code>#interesting_things</code> will always return either the collection I expect or a reasonable facscimile. It is a simple enough solution, but I definitely felt that message sink into place. Methods are objects and objects have API&rsquo;s: messages in and messages out. Make those messages deliberate, because if &ldquo;returning null from methods is bad, passing null into methods is worse.&rdquo;</p>

<h3>Protect Your Boundaries</h3>

<p>Controlling the messages going in to and coming out of your objects is one place you need to protect your boundaries, but what about objects from 3rd party libraries or frameworks? There are consequences of relying too heavily on a library API, and in Chapter 9: Boundaries, James Grenning shares a few of them. One system he was working with collected information by passing around a Map collection, which is a standard library data structure in Java. In the next version of Java, new capabilities were added, and in order to use the new feature they had to find everywhere the object was used and make the change.</p>

<blockquote><p>We&rsquo;ve seen systems that are inhibited from using [the new feature] because of the sheer magnitude of changes needed to make up for the liberal use of Maps.</p></blockquote>

<p>I recently had a similar experience when upgrading an application from Rails 3.0 to Rails 3.2, where there were drastic changes to how models record errors. Errors inherited from OrderedHash in Rails 3.0 and from ActiveModel in Rails 3.2 &mdash; very different object types. Every test that looked for errors called <code>errors.on</code> &mdash; now a deprecated method. Every place that looped over the collection with <code>errors.each</code> had to be changed to <code>errors.messages.each</code>, or the logic modified altogether. It is good practice to be distrustful of APIs that are likely to change, and while I don&rsquo;t believe that the Errors object ever seemed unstable, it has certainly made me extra cautious of calling 3rd party framework methods directly.</p>

<h3>Clean Code is not a &ldquo;nice-to-have&rdquo;</h3>

<p>Technical debt is not a decision to be okay with untested, brittle code that is impossible to build on &mdash; it is a decision to pursue a design that may not be scalable, but it can still be clean. It is tempting to declare &ldquo;Mission Accomplished&rdquo; when you have reached the point of working code, but the job is really only half done:</p>

<blockquote><p>It is not enough for code to work. Code that works is often badly broken. Programers who satisfy themselves with merely working code are behaving unprofessionally. They may fear that they don&rsquo;t have time to improve the structure and design of their code, but I disagree. Nothing has a more profound and long term degrading effect upon a development project than bad code. Bad schedules can be redone, bad requirements can be redefined. Bad team dynamics can be repaired. But bad code rots and ferments, becoming an inexorable weight that drags the team down.</p></blockquote>

<p>A story cannot be declared finished until the code is ammenable to change. In order to change code, it must be comprehensible and thoroughly tested. Compromising code quality to meet the demands of a schedule will only slow things down in the long run.</p>

<p><em>Clean Code</em> is a must read for all professional software developers. Leaving clean code is not just a kindness to the next developer (which is likely to be you), but is essential for growing a healthy codebase. Of course, &ldquo;to write clean code, you must first write dirty code and then clean it,&rdquo; and I look forward to learning new techniques as we tackle <em>Refactoring</em>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
