<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Read | keighty]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/categories/read/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-11T08:37:07-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[katie leonard]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Situations Matter]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/situations-matter/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-28T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/situations-matter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Situations-Matter-Understanding-Context-Transforms-ebook/dp/B005ERIS5S/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1396016834&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=situations+matter">Situations Matter</a> by Sam Sommers is an eye-opening study of the influence of context on human interactions. Social psychologists call it &ldquo;fundamental attribution error&rdquo;, which is a tendency to interpret someone else&rsquo;s behavior as stemming from their core characteristics, rather than to external circumstances. A simplistic example of attribution error is assuming that the person driving the speeding car is a reckless speed-freak rather than someone rushing a woman in labor to the hospital. Sommers has studied the power of situations over human interactions and how the attribution error interferes with our ability to empathize with the unfamiliar. I have read similar studies of how bias infiltrates our relationships, but what surprised me the most is how it also influences our perception of the self. <!--more--></p>

<h3>You&rsquo;re not the person you thought you were</h3>

<p>A provocative but aptly named chapter, Sommers overturns the concept of an &ldquo;authentic self&rdquo; with a simple fill-in-the-blanks exercise:</p>

<ol>
<li>I am _________________</li>
<li>I am _________________</li>
<li>I am _________________</li>
<li>I am _________________</li>
<li>I am _________________</li>
</ol>


<p>His study subjects were required to fill in 20 of these blanks, but 5 is enough to illustrate his point to the reader. The open-endedness of this exercise allows for a fantastic range of responses: &ldquo;I am 36 years old, I am hungry, I am tall, I am a lifelong learner&rdquo;. Taking the 20 questions test in different contexts will yield different definitions of yourself. Sommers has discovered that &ldquo;we tend to think of ourselves in terms of that which makes us distinctive&rdquo;, so your answers will have more to do with the people around you than with a fixed set of characteristics. A woman is more likely to include gender on her list if she is in a room full of men than if she is in a room full of women. So it seems that &ldquo;identity is malleable and personal preferences are constructed on the spot.&rdquo; Introspection will gain us little but a hazy snap-shot of our identity at any given moment.</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;It&rsquo;s refreshing to realize that you&rsquo;re not a finished product &mdash; that who you are in the here and now may not be the same person you&rsquo;ll be in the then and there. In fact, it&rsquo;s the opposite view of the self as a fixed entity that causes problems. When you assume that there&rsquo;s a true core self waiting to be discovered, that&rsquo;s when your potential seems limited and the world around you is full of threats to be rationalized away.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<p>One quality that is typically presumed to be fixed is intelligence. Challenging this truism, another study was conducted where students were grouped according to their belief that either intelligence is a stable attribute, or that their intellect can be changed. The researchers asked the students to predict the likelihood that they will attend a remedial language course, and then tracked their performance. It was found that among the students who fared poorly in the language course, those who viewed intelligence as a permanent, unchangeable trait were less likely to enroll in the remedial course &mdash; that is, to take steps in order to improve their performance. For students who believe that intelligence is fixed, a poor exam grade is a mark of their limitations rather than an opportunity for improvement. Students who believe that intelligence is malleable are more likely to show the stick-to-itiveness necessary for self-improvement.</p>

<p>Viewing the self less like a rigid Rubik&rsquo;s Cube to be solved, and more like Silly Putty that conforms to the shape of its container, will likely free up a lot of my time. Instead of trying to solve the puzzle. I can spend energy on finding the container that makes me happy&hellip; for the moment.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Ambition Gap - Leaning In]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/the-ambition-gap-lean-in/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-23T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/the-ambition-gap-lean-in</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I may be a little late to the game, but I am finally reading Sheryl Sandberg&rsquo;s &ldquo;Lean In&rdquo;, and right from the introduction I can understand why it caused such a stir when it came out in 2012. Sandberg addresses the issue of why there are relatively few women in leadership roles, and ways that women have held themselves back.<!--more--> Women earn more than 57% of undergraduate degrees and 60% of masters degrees, and yet hold less than 14% of C level positions. I always assumed that as women disproportionately fill the ranks of entry level positions, there would be a proportional increase of women filling senior level positions as well. Apparently this is not the case. &ldquo;The exodus of highly educated women is a major contributor to the leadership gap.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Surround your pullquote like this {" text to be quoted "}</p>

<h3>Too much Barbie or not enough Hillary?</h3>

<p>Sandberg is quick to link the relative derth of women in leadership roles on the messages of obedience and passivity we instill in girls and the general indulgence of opposite traits in boys (&ldquo;boys will be boys&rdquo;). &ldquo;Gender stereotypes introduced in childhood are reinforced throughout our lives and become self-fulfilling prophesies.&rdquo; While gender stereotypes have held women back in the past, today the difference is in their perceived options, not in perceived abilities. When the kindergarten-ers in Sandberg&rsquo;s story were asked what they wanted to be when they grew up they looked to the immediate role models around them. Call it a lack of imagination about one&rsquo;s future career, rather than a lack of ambition.</p>

<p>She has recently begun a campaign to <a href="http://banbossy.com/">ban the word &ldquo;bossy&rdquo;</a>, and while words have the power to shape our values, it is a passive approach to solving the problem. Boys don&rsquo;t show a propensity towards leadership in middle-school any more than girls show a propensity towards secretarial work. Sandberg&rsquo;s <a href="http://leanin.org/">&ldquo;Lean In&rdquo;</a> project comes closer to directly addressing the issue. She realizes that you can&rsquo;t be what you can&rsquo;t see", and works to raise the profiles of powerful women. When it becomes normal to have female leaders, I am sure we will find more girls expressing ambition. Likewise, when it becomes normal for men to share equally in care-giving, boys will begin making different choices.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Lean-In-Women-Work-Will/dp/0385349947/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1395756488&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=lean+in">Lean In: Women, Work, and the Will to Lead</a> by Sheryl Sandberg</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Value of Slow Transitions]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/the-value-of-transition/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-08T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/the-value-of-transition</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>The Why</h3>

<p>From <a href="http://bost.ocks.org/mike/constancy/">Object Constancy</a> by Mike Bostock:</p>

<blockquote><p>Animated transitions are pretty, but they also serve a purpose: they make it easier to follow the data. This is known as <strong>object constancy</strong>: a graphical element that represents a particular data point&hellip; can be tracked visually through the transition. This lessens the cognitive burden by using <strong>preattentive processing</strong> of motion rather than sequential scanning of labels.</p></blockquote>

<p>(The emphasis is mine)</p>

<h3>The How</h3>

<p>Object constancy is achieved through object identity: the data is bound to it&rsquo;s object by a shared unique identifier. This allows D3 to reuse the object when the data set is updated. Object identity is achieved by passing a key function to the data() method at the time of data binding:</p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>var data = [ // &lt;-A&lt;/p>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;pre>&lt;code>    {id: 0, value: "foo"},
</span><span class='line'>    {id: 1, value: "bar"},
</span><span class='line'>    {id: 2, value: "foo"},
</span><span class='line'>    {id: 3, value: "baz"},
</span><span class='line'>    {id: 4, value: "bar"}
</span><span class='line'>];
</span><span class='line'>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p>d3.selectAll(&ldquo;svg:g&rdquo;)&lt;/p>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;pre>&lt;code>.data(data, function(d){return d.id;});
</span><span class='line'>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p></span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Technique for Producing Ideas]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/a-technique-for-producing-ideas/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-04T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/a-technique-for-producing-ideas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B001C34HUS/ref=as_li_tf_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=B001C34HUS&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=bridgeforpoke-20">A Technique for Producing Ideas</a> by James Webb Young (1965)</p>

<p>Young proposes that all ideas are the result of five identifiable stages of rumination, whether they are followed consciously or not:</p>

<ol>
<li>Gather information, and not just what is specific to your problem domain. Novelty comes from mashing seemingly unrelated concepts together.</li>
<li>Review the information &mdash; collate your information in some fashion and go over it. A lot.</li>
<li>Do something else. Get distracted from whatever problem you are trying to solve.</li>
<li>&ldquo;Eureka! I have it!&rdquo;</li>
<li>Refine your idea &mdash; first drafts are never perfect, so keep polishing.</li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Neuroscience of Programming]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/programming-and-linguistics/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-27T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2014/programming-and-linguistics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3><a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/chris-parnin/scientists-begin-looking-_b_4829981.html">Scientists Begin Looking at Programmers' Brains: The Neuroscience of Programming</a> from The Huffington Post.</h3>

<blockquote><p>A new study provides new evidence that programmers are using language regions of the brain when understanding code and found little activation in other regions of the brain devoted to mathematical thinking.</p></blockquote>

<ul>
<li>Each programming language you learn requires expressing abstract concepts with a different syntax &mdash; and in the case of punctuation (~>, =>, :, {}, [], etc) an augmented alphabet. How is a programming language NOT like linguistics?</li>
</ul>


<blockquote><p>Besides a mathematical inclination, an exceptionally good mastery of one&rsquo;s native tongue is the most vital asset of a competent programmer. &mdash;Djikstra</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
