<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Rails4 | keighty]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/categories/rails4/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-12T11:01:19-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[katie leonard]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[No index.html, No Cry]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2013/no-indexhtml-no-cry/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-29T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.katieleonard.ca/blog/2013/no-indexhtml-no-cry</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Following along with <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Ruby-Rails-Tutorial-Addison-Wesley-Professional/dp/0321832051">Rails tutorial</a> by Michael Hartl, I built a sample app with a simple database, linking users to microposts in a twitter-like manner. Everything worked well locally, but when it came time to deploy on heroku, I ran across some interesting stumbling blocks:</p>

<h3>Rails 4 does not come with a default index.html</h3>

<p>There I was, gleefully watching the slug compile on heroku (after several abortive attempts I realized I had not moved the sqlite3 gem into the development environment &mdash; heroku doesn&rsquo;t like that). All seemed fine, I typed
<div>
  <pre><code class='java'>$ heroku open</code></pre>
</div>

and what greeted me? A 404 error page! Something has gone horribly wrong! I have been rejected by heroku! I try again from the beginning, ensuring I have followed all the steps.. what could I have missed? Same result. But, Mr. Hartl, said it was easy&hellip; what was I missing?</p>

<p>After some digging, I found a <a href="https://devcenter.heroku.com/articles/rails4-getting-started">heroku tutorial</a> on getting started with the shiny new Rails 4. Deep inside this article, I found the magic words:</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;Note: that Rails 4 no longer has a static index page in production, if you’re using a new app, there may be no root page.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<p>Orly? Are you saying that the 404 error I was getting was actually generated by my properly deployed app? YES! I made some obvious change to the html
<div>
  <pre><code class='html'>&lt;title&gt;You made it!&lt;/title&gt;</code></pre>
</div>

and redeployed. TADA!</p>

<p>Awesome.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
